And then DevOps came along.
And DevOps and cloud as well because
infrastructure was on demand. You didn't
have to order it months and months in
advance. That then increased the
velocity again. And we had to we had to
completely change like the rulebook
around operations and how you did that
job. It became much more about
automation. It became much more about
self-healing and like resilience
engineering. And now here we are with
AI.
You're listening to the AI Native Dev
brought to you by Tesela.
On today's episode of the AI Native Dev,
joining myself Simon Maple is Hannah
Foxwell. Hannah, welcome. Thank you for
having me. Oh, it's a pleasure to have
you on here. Now now Hannah is an
independent consultant in and around
platform engineering, security, and AI.
And Hannah, you and I used to work
together at at Snyk many moons ago. We
did. All the best people work at Snyk,
obviously.
All the best people. Yeah, absolutely.
You were a product director for
container security at Snyk. And then
prior to that you were a director of
platform services at VMware. You've done
a bunch of community stuff as well,
including the DevOps Days organizer,
OpenUK ambassador. And in your spare
time, if there's few minutes that you
have as well on top of all that, you
also ran an amazing conference which we
attended and we sponsored last year
called AI for the rest of us which was a
great success as well. Um
Yes, I did. I'm not very good at sitting
still. I don't know whether you do or
not. How do you find the
time?
I was going to take a career break.
Genuinely, I was going to take a career
break. And then I got bored and I
thought I know what I'll do. I know what
I'll run an AI conference single-handed
in 5 months. Yeah.
And that's what that's what I spent a
lot of last year doing. But it was
fabulous, wasn't it? There'll be another
one this year. It was. Oh, amazing. It
has to be good and then you get to do it
again. And it was good and therefore
we'll do it That's always the what you
get when you do good work is just more
work, right? So, you've you've run an
amazing conference and now you have to
do it all over again from demand of
everyone who enjoyed that conference
last year, which is brilliant. Your
background very heavily in the DevOps
space. Talk us through a few of the
things that you've obviously the DevOps
Days one of the organizers there. How
did you get into DevOps originally? My
DevOps like origin story is actually
back from like my early career as a
release manager. Everyone talks about
those silos between dev and ops or the
wall of confusion and things like that
and I was literally little Hannah in her
early 20s sat
on top of that wall of confusion trying
to interpret what I was hearing from dev
from what I was hearing from ops and
build a cohesive plan that everyone
could buy into.
And very early on in the DevOps
movement, I
saw it as a way to solve a very real and
painful problem that I had experienced
personally, but I knew that almost all
organizations were experiencing. And I
was like there has to be a better way. I
didn't have the answer. I I didn't know
what that better way was, but I knew
that there was a very real problem to be
solved.
And so yeah, that's my DevOps origin
story. And yeah, I think if I was to
describe my career, it has always been
about building like building better like
engineering teams, building better
organizations. Like not just a single
dev team, but like all of the mechanics
that happen around software development
that make it successful. That naturally
led me to take a bit of a detour into
product leadership because it doesn't
matter how good you build it, you have
to build the right thing. But very much
still in the developer tool space, very
much centered on developer experience
and developer productivity and that's
where we work together at Snyk.
Yeah, amazing. And in terms of with that
kind of a background we we were that's
behind us or that's when we when we look
back we see the changes that we made, we
see the lessons that we learned in the
DevOps world. Looking forward now of
course with some of the challenges and
some of the amazing benefits that AI can
provide us with. We're sat here on the
cusp of another cultural team change and
we're once again needing to answer many
of the same questions in terms of how do
we adopt this technology correctly
within our teams, how do we change our
teams to effectively make best use of
AI within our applications within our
software that we build but also from the
team point of view, how do we use AI to
perform better
as a team as well. There's going to be a
lot of consistency between the
challenges that we faced and probably
some in the ways in which we solve
those. How do you I guess maybe looking
back at DevOps first before we then
start looking at the challenges that AI
provides us from a team and organization
point of view and a ways of working
point of view and what we can actually
practically do maybe today even to help
us with those challenges. When we look
back at the the DevOps space, what do
you feel like we as a industry did well
and did absolutely appallingly at when
addressing or trying to take on I guess
the benefits of DevOps, the things that
DevOps can provide us with. What what
were the highs and lows of that would
you say? Yeah, I think there's there's
one really important similarity and it's
that sort of bottom-up engineering
driven adoption. And I think DevOps was
really such a like engineering led
movement, wasn't it? It was like this is
a better way of doing things and I think
we have seen that almost overnight.
We're talking about one or two years
which isn't very much time in tech.
Like the vast majority of software
developers will be using AI tools in
their workflow, in in everyday workflow.
It's one of the personas or like the the
industries that has really immediately
felt the benefits of generative AI and
what that technology can do for us
today. So, I think that's one of the
similarities. I think on the flip side,
one of the differences is that AI is
obviously touching every role. It's not
just touching developers, whereas DevOps
was like very incubated within the
developer community. I don't think many
businesses really cared about it too
much. This was just about us getting our
house in order. I think everybody cares
about AI.
Back in 2012, so we're we're talking
about a while ago, over a decade ago.
Back in 2012, the CIO,
like the big boss at the company I was
working at, he said, "Don't talk to me
about DevOps." Every time like an
engineering leader or an architect or
someone was like, "Behold the future and
it is DevOps." He was like, "Stop
talking to me about that." Because he
just couldn't see like the the return on
investment, the business rationale
behind it. Because it was all new and it
was unproven. Whereas today with AI,
your CIO, your CTO, your CEO is going,
"I want generative AI in everyone's
pockets, in everyone's jobs. I want that
productivity boost. I want it yesterday.
Go." And I think there's this real
pressure top-down to couple with that
bottom-up engineering enthusiasm that we
have for these tools, which is new. I
think that's really exciting. Yeah,
that's interesting. When we think about
who are the skeptics, looking at it from
that point of view, within AI today, you
have the various groups. Some people
absolutely adore AI and are fully all in
and they believe it's the future, if not
today, but very soon as models improve
and and and technology gets better.
There are others who look at AI and so
skeptical of it and and and don't really
want to use it because they think they
can do better today. Would you say
that's like similar to the DevOps space
as well in terms of people who are
trying to put barriers up or people who
have more of that inertia not to lean
into the new technologies. Yeah, I think
that there's always going to be a fear
of change and that little voice inside
your head that goes, "What does it mean
for me? Am I going to lose my job? Are
the things that I enjoy about my job
going away? What does the future look
like?" Unfortunately, I think for those
of us who choose a career in technology,
that's relentless and comfort with
change and ambiguity
is actually one of the things that will
like set you up for success. But let me
flip the conversation around. Like where
do you sit on that like broad spectrum
of a pessimist or maybe like a
catastrophist? I don't think you are cuz
you're running an AI podcast. But on the
other end of the scale, we get optimist,
but we also get almost like that cultish
sort of hype around AI where all of the
challenges and limitations are brushed
away. Like those will be solved in the
next few years. The good versions are
coming. Like where are you on that like
on that spectrum?
It's a great question. I'd like to think
I'm quite a realist in that space where
I I see the benefits, right? The
benefits are are fairly obvious. I think
it still feels magic when you ask it to
do stuff and it provides you with
answers and
it is quite amazing what it can do
today. It's far from perfect and and we
can see the levels of where we are today
in using it. You still today need to use
it in somewhat of an assisted manner.
And while I think the future is a much
more autonomous space, I'm quite that
realist in thinking we have come a long
way. There is still a long way to go and
we need to be almost a little bit
careful in how we talk about AI cuz I
can see so many people who are almost
very blasé with the way that they're
expressing what their app or what their
technology can do. And actually, there's
a big and me and Guy were talking about
this just the other day. There's a big
difference between that demo and the
actual real world use case. And it's
easy to get any product to work well in
a demo, but when you actually want it to
to work well day in day out on real
world applications, it's way, way
harder. And I think today we're still
very much in that demo space. Unless the
tool is well attended and you can build
up that trust going forward.
going to say trust. It's about trust.
It's about reliability. And these tools
have to earn it with their consistency,
which AI doesn't really do consistency,
does it? It's the whole point. It's
non-deterministic. And consistency
versus accuracy versus reliability. One
of those words or a combination is the
right thing, but it helps to build that
trust. And then we get to a point where
we can really feel the benefits of it
because once you have proven that it's
good, then we can build much more
autonomous systems. I'm very excited
about the world of AI agents. And again,
everyone's talking about AI agents. I'm
going to be incredibly boring and I'm
going to talk about it as well. But if
you can offload a lot of the repetitive
mundane work to an AI agent or a team of
AI agents that work in unison, like how
liberating is that for the humans
involved? I've worked as as part of huge
enterprise companies, tens of thousands
of people in these organizations, and
the
mechanics of operating those companies
is painful. Absolutely painful. And
that's an area where I think AI is going
to absolutely change the game.
Yeah, absolutely.
So let's talk a little bit about teams
and culturally how AI can potentially
change the organization, how we expect
it to change the organization going
forward. And then also, what can we can
actually do practically today to prepare
ourselves for these potential changes?
When we start a little bit longer term,
how do you see development teams
potentially
changing the way software is built, the
way the organizations have to adapt to
those changes in development.
Let me talk about like the humans first
because I think that's always a good
place to start. So, I've seen AI tools
in the hands of a really experienced
sort of principal engineer
and you can get literally months worth
of work done in a day because you know
exactly what you're asking it for. You
use your knowledge in unison with the
automation tooling that you've got at
your disposal to ask for the right thing
and the right thing come out and I think
that is unbelievable. Like it's
absolutely mind-blowing. I think at the
other end of the spectrum, not your
principal engineer but your new
engineer, I think this is called AI
native dev but those will be the AI
native dev. If you're coming into
software development today, you're not
learning in the same way. You've got
that these tools at your disposal and
your learning journey is going to look
very different. Mhm. And then there's
all the in-betweenies, the people who
are on their learning journey and they
started off in one mode of operation and
now with these new tools, they have to
switch and I think though like those are
the people who are going to have the
hardest time transitioning because they
don't necessarily have all of that
in-depth knowledge that the your
principals and your staff engineers have
to ask for the right thing and to know
with confidence that what it's giving
you is the right thing.
And I think then we need to look at,
okay, how do we make
teams with all different like a mix of
skill levels successful? And it's not
that different to what we do today. You
want your
senior engineers, your principals and
your staff engineers, you want them
mentoring everybody
at different stages. You want them to be
scaling their impact rather than just
picking up tasks off the backlog and
executing. So, I don't think that's that
much different. I think it could be an
uncomfortable transition for some
engineers who don't necessarily yet have
like that depth of experience to know
with confidence that the AI tooling is
giving them the right answer but I think
there have to be those guard rails and
that safety net.
And ideally, it would be coming from a a
mentor type figure to figure it out. The
education piece though is super
interesting I find in terms of the
number of times I've been asked by
people who are coming into the industry,
what is it I need to learn today? Is it
worth still learning various programming
languages or not and things like this?
And I guess one of the things that we
probably should focus on fairly early is
education, right? And from what you were
just saying. But it's not actually that
different to the education you would
have done anyway. It's like you're maybe
it's maybe reframed. So instead of a
blank sheet of paper and you having to
write the program from scratch, you are
now
presented with something to respond to.
But it is the same knowledge you need to
be able to make sure that is a quality
or quality built in that you haven't
made any silly mistakes so that it's
doing what it's supposed to do. And and
that's interesting because I feel a lot
of the details of development will will
be
certainly around implementation will be
lost because if we can rely on AI to
provide us with implementations, we need
to think less about the implementations
and more about how we build in terms of
the architecture, the patterns that we
use and and so forth. Do we feel like
that is potentially something that will
be better for a developer, a junior
developer to perhaps learn than
necessarily the implementations if that
is being handled more for us? Do you see
like a shift in the perspective of
education? May maybe more even about
what makes an application good versus
just what makes code performant or There
are so many tools at your disposal. You
can obviously use just like linting
tools to find structural issues with
your code. You can use security, static
code analysis tools and things like that
to catch any obvious issues. And so we
have all of this stuff at our disposal.
We were talking before this, weren't we,
about us being over an age where we grew
up without the internet. And I think
it's about being a software developer of
an age where you didn't have all of
these tools at your disposal. It can be
it will be interesting to see whether
anything is lost along the way and like
how it changes and how it changes the
profession. Just the internet has
completely changed society.
And for those of us who are very used to
the should I call them old ways of
coding right now? I don't know. The
pre-AI software development. If we take
from our DevOps best practice or like
what we learn from folks who were more
um
I guess skeptical of of DevOps. What can
we learn in terms of when we think about
encouraging our development teams to be
more AI savvy, to to to to buy into AI
more into in in the in the future ways
of of development. What can we learn to
avoid
inertia when we're making that
transition to more of an AI native or I
just generally AI assisted way of
developing. Are there things that we can
do better or learn from that DevOps
spaces to how we can encourage people to
buy into these types of new paradigm
shifts? Yeah, I always come back to that
really simple loop of build, measure,
learn. Build, measure, learn and the
build, measure, learn is obviously
the methodology that you use to ensure
that your product development is on
track, you know. You create a
hypothesis, test that hypothesis,
measure the impact that it's had and
learn and then improve. And I think you
could talk about Agile methodologies.
You could talk about DevOps. You could
talk about platform engineering because
that's applying user experience and
product management to internal tools.
Like that's completely transferable to
your AI tools for developers as well.
So, it's about making space to
experiment and to do that build,
measure, learn cycle and it being okay
for your learning to be like that was
the wrong way. Let's not do that again.
Uh-huh.
Cuz I think everything's evolving so
quickly. And I think it's hard to look
back and remember what what you were
thinking and feeling like 15 years ago,
10 years ago in your career because you
don't have the benefit of hindsight and
confirmation bias and things, but
I do think that the teams that were real
leaders in the DevOps space, in the
cloud native space, cloud engineering, I
think they were the ones that were
willing to try something different, to
throw out the old way, and to go "Let's
experiment. Let's incubate some new
practices. Let's measure the success of
them and learn from it." And they were
okay with not being right first time or
not being not having the answer cuz I
don't think that, you know, like we talk
about whether you're like an AI optimist
or pessimist or things like that. I am
just like so here to ride this roller
coaster. And there's going to be ups and
there's going to be downs.
And I'm like, "But whatever, it's going
to be really fun." If I could go back
like 10 years with the DevOps space, I
would have been a lot more vocal like
publicly about what I was doing and what
we were learning from it because I felt
a little bit of impostery back then.
It's all if no one else is doing it this
way, maybe I'm wrong. It's like, "Oh,
like we're all inventing. We're all
inventing and experimenting and if we
share what we're learning, then we all
get better." And I think that's where
we're at. We're at that messy
experimental incubation phase where
there's no right answer. Uh-huh.
Yeah. And if you And if you can measure
that and then share your success and you
can say, "Look, I was doing this. It
took me this long. Now I can do it with
actually far less effort and
asynchronously to other work I'm doing
and it takes me this long." You can
share that and say, "Look, who else
wants to learn from these ways of
working?" And I guess for those who are
more skeptical, it's not just about time
as well. It's about the frustrations
that those things can that those
previous tasks can cause cuz if you're
taking away jobs that people don't want
to do and whatever that is and actually
providing people with more fun things
and that could be an area as well. I
guess from the team point of view, in
DevOps, one of the things actually if we
lean into DevSecOps, one of the things
that I love seeing companies and
organizations do was build out these
security champion style groups and
having folks who were almost like
bleeding edge learning how to do things
and then sharing that with other teams
so that others can adopt it so that not
everyone has to trip over the same
barriers at the same time. Yeah,
absolutely. It's
building communities of practice is
really good. Having those internal
champions and advocates. Some
takes a little bit of effort to bring
people together around that because
Yeah. everyone's busy. Like everyone's
so busy and the first sort of the year
after like ChatGPT came out, I hadn't
really touched it cuz I was like
blinkers on. I was like, I've got a lot
of work to do. I've got very important
work to do. And I didn't have time to
raise my head and look around and be
like, what's going on here? But I think
there are a lot of people who are still
like that or maybe they haven't
experimented with the technology to a
point where it can really have an impact
on their day-to-day lives. They've just
scratched the surface. Maybe it's
hallucinated at you and you've lost a
little bit of faith in it. Maybe you
haven't spent the time to learn how to
write a good structured prompt. I'm sure
there are a lot of folks who are like me
who are like the skeptical or like maybe
a bit disengaged at the moment just
because of the time available and the
learning curve that you have to go
through. And some of the absolute the
hackathon has made a comeback in a big
way, hasn't it? But one of the best
things you can do for helping people
learn is to make sure that it's low
pressure. Make sure that it's not tied
to delivery or deliverable. Make it
experimental. Make it fun. Make it
social and then people will engage.
People will have have a go and I think
that's I think I genuinely think like
the hackathon has made such a big
comeback because it is such an effective
way to get people engaged with and to
get people to pick up these new tools in
a safe environment where there's no
pressure and no fear of failure. Yeah.
Yeah, interesting. And actually, yeah,
the hackathon style what can we do with
AI today kind of thing just just trying
to play with it. I saw a tweet or maybe
it was a Blue Sky post actually and it
was someone who said before you use AI,
just think about if you can do this in
normal coding prior pre-AI style
technologies before you do that. And I
thought that was an interesting tweet in
terms of almost people are almost too
inclined to use AI too quickly and I
feel like that tweet was maybe a little
bit badly worded. They probably should
have said something like think about if
you can do this in conventional
programming ways better. So, don't use
AI for the sake of using AI if there are
better ways of doing it. Do you feel
like one of the one of the pushbacks
could be that if people are trying to
use AI too much people will almost get
frustrated in it actually being a
providing them with worse ways of
working. Do you feel like we're almost
being pushed or pressured into AI? Yeah,
there's there's a lot of like LLM
washing. I don't know what the question
is, but the answer is use an LLM. They
are It is revolutionary technology
because of the way you interact with it
because it's natural language. It's very
accessible to a lot of people who would
not have previously been able to write
code. Um, there are process automation
tools out there. If this then that and
you want to draw a flowchart of all the
different scenarios that you might get
as input and you want to write a be very
thorough in your analysis of writing
down like every permutation of every
output. That's all technically very
feasible. Or you could just throw that
process at an LLM and tell it whether it
got to the right answer or not. And very
quickly you've got a working prototype
and I can see why why so alluring. I can
absolutely see why so alluring. It's not
deterministic and if you've got a
process that needs to be predictable and
specific, maybe it's not the right thing
for you. But, when you're talking about
there's always like the support desk or
the call center option when you've got
unpredictable inputs, it can be very
good. And you might actually you might
say actually I do need very specific
outputs, but I need maybe this and maybe
need this filtering layer to help
organize all of these inputs into
buckets. And then again, and if this
then that program won't really won't
catch everything in the same way that an
LLM will have a go. They're very good at
having a go, aren't they? Yeah, yeah,
absolutely.
And I think that's probably an area that
we need to
we ourselves need to change as well in
recognizing
it's non-deterministic in the sense of
any and it can be wrong in a
non-deterministic way. There's a good
chat earlier on the podcast with Caleb
Seaman who was talking about having a an
LLM
um provide you with information about
how many vulnerabilities you have in
your code and if it runs five times and
it says you've got one vulnerability and
then it runs a fifth time and it says
there's no vulnerability, how do you
deal with that when we're thinking very
much in a deterministic way of is this
code vulnerable or not vulnerable? And I
think we need to
be much more mindful about the
limitations and the output that LLMs
provide and and deal with that in our
ways of working. What one other question
that I I would love to ask is when we
think about the changes in teams, for
example, platform engineering teams um
DevOps engineer, these types of roles
which are roles and teams which were
largely created through almost everyone
trying to do everything
themselves followed by it would actually
be wonderful if we had this kind of this
paved road or path
Yes, yeah, yeah. do this. And then you
have people who support those services
or support those ways of working and
it's okay to go off-road, but you have
to support yourself and these teams are
helping us with this more paved road. I
guess if we draw that parallel to AI
now, do we see AI engineers and folks
like that joining these same teams? Do
we see developers today maybe taking
that more upon themselves in the same
way that we did with DevOps? What do you
see I guess today and what advice would
you give for how we can do that most
effectively? I agree. I think there's
that you have two types of users. There
is your technical user. Like you in the
platform engineering, I'm providing a
shared platform that people can use and
people can leverage, people can plug
aspects of their application into this
platform, people can plug aspects of
their processes into this. Like it's a
shared resource. I think that is a
pattern that we are absolutely going to
see evolving and it doesn't matter
whether in the back end just like
self-hosting an open-source LLM like
Llama or Mistral or whether you're
backing off into an API that's hosted by
Microsoft or Google opening up. It won't
really matter because the
user interface is something that you've
provided like a portal internally. The
other aspect of it and this is where
we're going to get sprawl is the the
sort of the business user who can write
a prompt. They're not in engineering,
but you see so many startups which have
focused on solving a problem in a
vertical for that user. And they're
offering the whole stack. And I think
there's a lot of shadow IT that's
probably going to happen with different
AI tools that are tailored specifically
for a certain persona within your
business. Mhm. And that's way out of
platform engineering. That's maybe
delivered through a SaaS solution. Maybe
it's an AI tool that you don't even
really know is like AI tool underneath
the hood. Maybe it's just a tool that
you use every day. And I think in the
same way it's really hard to understand
your software bill of materials,
understanding your AI landscape, and the
AI sprawl that's happening across all of
your different tools and platforms, all
of your different roles and business
processes, is going to be really
challenging. It's already happening.
It's already happening. And you have to
decide what's okay and what's not. You
have to put some guardrails around that.
But most importantly, you have to
educate your team about what's okay and
what's not okay in your organization.
Don't feed customer information in a
free tier of a SaaS product, for
example, because they're probably using
the free tier users a trading data. You
probably shouldn't be disclosing any
personally identifiable information
about your customers anyway to any third
party. But
that's a huge education piece because
it's not okay to not put these tools in
people's hands if it can make them so
much better at their job. But you do
have to make sure that you have some
visibility of what tools are in your
portfolio. And so, that's steering a
little bit away from the developer
tooling piece because I think a platform
engineering team, they have maybe more
visibility into the engineering domain
than they do into the business domain
and what's happening there. But and
security
like security is probably jumping up and
down and losing their mind
how to mitigate these risks as well. But
uh Yeah. Yeah. It is interesting though
that you bring up a few really good
points there actually. I think one is
that this is far broader than DevOps in
the sense of DevOps was there to help
software delivery, software development,
and things like that. It's very heavily
based in the engineering space and the
operation space. AI is far broader than
that and actually has implications and
benefits across the organization. So,
this is one and I think the second one
that you mentioned which is really
really good is
the idea of what can you do
and what shouldn't you do. Like you
know, what can and can't you do based on
limitations of basically company
guardrails, company guidelines of what
you can and can't provide the the models
and so forth. And as soon as we go
outside of the engineering department
and those more technical spaces,
you lose that intrinsic kind of
technical or mechanical sympathy of
what's actually happening under the
covers in these LLMs. And so people
might accidentally mistakenly provide an
LLM with too much information, too much
business sensitive information, and
potentially leak company data and so
forth. And that's all before we think
about the what's the best way of doing
something. It's more the
can we do it? Can we not do it?
It's day zero, isn't it? This is day
zero. Yeah. I think it's probably a
combination, isn't it? It's probably
combination, I think. There will be I'm
like I've always worked in these like
very complicated enterprise I've I've
always worked in that space. These are
where the really hard challenges are.
And I think when I'm talking to people
about what they're using and how they're
using it, there are some teams that
can't use a SaaS solution. They're
regulated environment, very sensitive
data, maybe it's banking, telco,
whatever.
And they're going down the self-hosted
route. And so it's a very platform
engineering, it's very platform centric.
And so one of the folks I'm working with
actually called Helix. They're building
the sort of private AI stack. That's
their mission to empower these companies
so that they can get a similar
experience internally on their own
hardware as they would using a SaaS or
an IaaS kind of solution. They can't go
to Google or Microsoft or OpenAI for
those things. Yeah. One of the things
that I've been mulling over is actually
whether or not it's an and instead of
like an or. Do you go left or do you go
right? Or do you actually support cuz
every business has very sensitive
information. Does every business
actually need to support their own
private GenAI stack for certain
processes? And then certain less
sensitive, more day-to-day, maybe more
creative, maybe marketing, maybe stuff
like that. Maybe you can use some of the
SAS tools and that is the right answer.
Yeah. But and being a little bit mindful
about what that's like I said like that
landscape of AI solutions is going to
look like in your organization. Maybe
Yeah.
But getting ahead of it and making a
decision about what you need and what
you don't instead of letting it sprawl
organically, new solutions popping up
all over the place.
Yeah. And and if I draw a parallel again
back to let's say DevSecOps and security
champions, I used to hear the same
question or the same problem space a few
times whereby there general company
security guard roles in which an
organization wants this kind of a
security champions program to help
educate everyone, whichever department
you're in, about good security hygiene
within your organization. And then you
have the much more focused
group which is purely around development
and about good security practices within
your coding. Everything from
vulnerabilities all the way through
where you store data, all that kind of
stuff.
And and people used to always say, you
know, should this be the same group? And
typically what we saw was people who
tried to make that the same group
actually made it less relevant for
everyone because all of a sudden there's
some stuff which is completely
irrelevant to others if someone in
marketing is getting information about
how to use third-party libraries. I
don't even know what this is.
Vice versa, if people were in
development getting extremely high-level
information which is there effectively
they already know super super well, but
it's like they they almost like feel a
bit embarrassed or or bored to have to
go through this type of education. Is
this going to be similar where we almost
have a set of AI education for an
organization and then a very specific
set of set of organization we keep these
as separate almost like programs of
education and maybe this is similar to
as we were talking with the platform
groups. Yeah, definitely. I think like
the enablement and the education that
you provide to your teams. I'm trying to
think about an example that I've been
through. So, everybody gets the training
on like physical security, don't they?
It's like what's what to do and not to
do with your hardware and things like
that cuz that's a commonality, but then
I can envisage like a very
role-based enablement process for and
this is the suite of AI tools that we
use here and here are the best practices
that we've uncovered for being the best
at your job. Not every job, but your
job. And that's would look very
fundamentally different for technical
teams than it would do non-technical
teams. So, I think it's an investment,
isn't it? It's an investment and it's a
such a difficult investment to make when
I'm sat here going, "We don't know what
the future looks like." Like
everything's changing every 5 minutes
and it's really exciting. It's like,
"Well, yeah, you're going to spend 6
months developing a like a training
program only for it to be redundant the
moment it's launched." I think like you
said, something that's more organic and
evolving like a community of practice or
a champions program might be the right
thing right now. Yeah. And as some of
these best practices kind of solidify
and like you figure out, "Okay, this
works for us and this doesn't." Maybe
then you add it to like your onboarding
process for new employees. Maybe then
you do some more formal training. I'm
not sure. I am interested if anybody who
is listening to this has any insights
because I am just genuinely curious
about how big organizations are tackling
this. I know how I would think about it,
but I'm not doing it in the real world.
So,
Yeah.
And I guess if we think about that
listener who let's say is a developer
working within a team and they're
thinking maybe in a year or two how
their job might change. I think we're
both like agreeing AI is certainly not
removing jobs from development, but what
would be the biggest changes would you
say that developer can expect in their
teams and in their ways of working in
the next couple of years, would you say?
That's a million-dollar question, isn't
it? No, no. This is how I think about
it. Lived and experienced that sort of
the switch from maybe waterfall software
delivery processes where releases were
once every 6 months, once every 3
months, like very rigid to Agile. And
when I experienced that, that increased
the pressure on the operations team to
the point where they they became the
bottleneck. They could not cope with
that extra velocity of the development
team.
And then DevOps came along.
And DevOps and cloud as well because
infrastructure was on demand. You didn't
have to order it months and months in
advance. That then increased the
velocity again, and we had to completely
change like the rulebook around
operations and how you did that job. It
became much more about automation. It
became much more about self-healing and
like resilience engineering. And now
here we are with AI.
And it's okay. So, the bit where you
write the code, cuz I think we have all
been optimizing our engineering teams
around maximizing focus time writing
code. I would say that was previously my
mission as an engineering manager. I
don't want my team distracted. I want
them focused on the task. What if that's
not the bottleneck anymore? What's
What's the bottleneck? It's not time
writing code. Writing code is the easy
bit. Yeah.
And actually,
I think you go up the process again. I
think you start to look at product, and
you start to think about what are the
product management practices that we
need in place to make sure that we are
doing that build measure learn cycle
as efficiently as possible. What happens
if you can prototype something in a day?
What then? Do you just ship it? Do you
like ship it to all your users or do you
need
to actually get really good at AB
testing? Like I know a lot of companies
aren't. Do you actually have to get a
little bit better about testing your
hypotheses? Do you have to get a little
bit better about
progressive delivery where you can roll
out a feature to cohorts of your user
base and really test that you are
building the right thing. Cuz I think
actually there is a real danger that
another step change, another increase in
developer velocity,
it's going to in a lot of places
encourage feature sprawl.
Every feature that you can think of is
built and every product it goes through
that
enshitification process. It's like
eventually the feature bloat is so much
that it becomes a different product,
becomes unusable and so on. I think
that's the interesting area for me. I
think it's where is that
How do we like fine-tune that
build-measure-learn cycle and we do a
much better job of the measure and learn
than we do
currently. Cuz I've worked in software
development for a long time
and I know, even I have done a really
bad job of the measure and learn bit
because
the vast majority of your time is
focused on build.
That's the bottleneck. You put all your
energy into build and once you've built
something, you're immersed in the next
build. All right. That's where you
That's where my head is at the moment. I
I really I really love that perspective
just in terms of
trying to foresee the next bottleneck
because this will take out a bottleneck
to the extent that it will accelerate
that so fast that we're going to almost
be caught out by the next bottleneck and
I think at times when we look at, let's
say, a number of features that we could
implement, we've never thought about
what happens if we could implement all
of these.
shouldn't implement all of them? Like
it's yeah, it's like with great power
comes great responsibility. Just because
we can doesn't mean we should. And I
think like
some of these some of these practices
they're just they're not as common as
you might think. The diligence, the
grand A/B testing, the diligence around
measuring our success, the user
feedback, like like how many people go
through a round of user feedback on on
their new features before they push it
to production. From my experience
anyway, we're all in execution mode.
Yeah. Building the thing is your focus,
and we can only build so many things.
And then you get this
confirmation bias that you must have
built the right thing, so you ship it,
you market it, and then you're all
terribly surprised it doesn't get used.
Um
So we'll effectively go away from that
point of view of we don't necessarily
need to prioritize because we only have
time to build X number of things. Now we
need to think about we should prioritize
based on the needs of what people are
doing. And and some people are are very
lucky in terms of maybe having the
option of doing both today because they
have large teams
yeah, like
like the future is here, it's just not
evenly distributed. Some teams are have
to look at this. They've got very
data-driven decision-making processes in
place.
But if I was putting my money on it, I
would say that a lot of teams have had
similar experiences to me where
the build part of build, measure, learn
is what takes up most of your time um
and energy because that's where the
bottleneck is currently. Yeah, and I
think it's
an immensely good thing that we think
more about that as developers as well
because
the focus shouldn't be on build, and the
focus should be much more around that,
thinking about the user need, the the
use case of what a user is trying to do
with this. And as a result, building
tools and applications that are designed
for developers rather than over-rotating
so much on how we design and how we
build this thing that we're actually not
focusing enough on the experience and
things like that. So a movement across
to that, which will be built into that
measure and and and learn cycle, is very
very needed and very very valuable to a
lot of organizations, I think.
Yeah. Yeah, and that goes back to what
we started the conversation on, which is
one of the lessons learned from DevOps.
15 years into the DevOps transformation
and building this community, what are we
talking about? Developer experience.
We're talking about user experience.
We're talking about making it easy to do
the right thing.
Yeah. It's a forever lesson that we'll
keep unlearning and relearning, like
user experience above everything.
Amazing. Hannah, we could talk for
another hour or so quite comfortably,
I'm sure, but this has been super
valuable. It's It's interesting to keep
bringing up actually, I feel that the
the DevOps lessons because it's
definitely a parallel that we can draw
with this existing movement. So, super
grateful for you sharing some of those
perspectives on that and I love the So,
what was the loop? It was build,
measure, learn, right?
Yes, build, build, measure, learn.
Build, measure, learn.
A very valuable a very valuable cycle
for us to keep repeating. Yeah, thank
you very much. Thank you very much for
joining us today, Hannah. Great to catch
up and hear your experiences. And for
those listening on the episode, thanks
again for tuning in and I hope to have
you tune in to the next episode shortly.
Thank you very much. Bye.
Thanks for tuning in. Join us next time
on the AI Native Dev, brought to you by
Tesler.